香水的起源
可以追溯到公元前2,000年到3千年
古希腊、古美索不达米亚、古埃及、古波斯
他们都有着各种香料
香油用于仪式的记录
但现代香水的流行
归功于300年前不爱洗澡的法国人
传说呢中世纪的欧洲
他们认为水会让毛孔张开
从而染上疾病
所以大家就更喜欢擦拭身体
而不是直接洗
传说中路易十四每年只洗一回
但这样一来
大家的体味就会有点重
那就需要香料来进行压制
19世纪中
现代化学工业成功合成了香豆素
香兰素等等这样的人工香料
才解除了
只能从大自然中获取味道的限制
打开了香水行业的现代版图
你有没有想过
平均每30秒就能卖出一瓶的香奈儿5号
年均狂捞5,000万欧的迪奥真我
他们都是怎么做出来的
传说中比宇航员人数还少的调香师
究竟是天赋异禀
还是说人人都有机会做呢
配方师带你
来位于巴黎凯旋门旁边的高级调香中心
来一探香水的究竟
真不愧是调香中心
空气都香到爆炸
来迎接我的
这位优雅的女士拉着我
开始了今天的真香之旅
现在呢
我们可以用来调配香水的人工香料
多达上千种
例如柠檬味的香茅醛
紫罗兰花味的紫罗兰酮
还有木质调的方樟醇等等等等
1,000种香料的原料
就有1,000的1,000次方种组合方案
你需要有优秀的鼻子
能分出这么多香味的细微差异
还要有丰富的化学知识
所以说
这个调香师真的是难度非常大的职业
而这样的人
我身边就有一位
我听过这么一个传言
调香师在入学考试的时候
他们会给你很多相似的这个味道
让你闻让你分辨
那你需要分辨出多少
多少种物质的这个味道
才有资格做调香师
is that true、 so i can't speak too much on the test
because they are kept confidential
but what i can say is that
it's a little bit more complicated than that
so the olfactive test is really just one small initial part of
what is actually
a six to nine month process to enter the perfumery school
so yes there is an olfactive exam that's quite in depth
but after that to be accepted into the school
you need six to nine months of interviews
and other types of tests to really make sure
the candidate is well rounded
没想到进调香师学校居然这么难
Ashley跟我说呢
有时候折腾了大半年
最后一个学生都没招到
看来这份既靠天赋又靠努力的职业
真的就是宁缺毋滥啊
那做香水的时候
你们会有一些公式吗
比如说a成分加上b成分
等于薰衣草味的
等等
还是说就说调香是一种纯自我的创作
每个人的作品都不一样呢
so more than you know the one plus
one gives you two or ingredient a plus ingredient
b gives you a rose it's much more like learning notes
and like in music
and so once you learn all your notes then
you can make a chord right and with a certain amount of chords
then you make a song and certain amount of songs
you can make a symphony
so there's there's a lot more of this type of building blocks
it's much more like composing than adding
because that's also how nature does it and in the school
you're really learning from nature so in the morning
you go when you pick a rose from the garden
you smell the rose
you see how nature composed its symphony
and you really try
and do the same nature's really the best teacher
but i think it's a bit closer to to music
because you're also trying to evoke emotion
with fragrance creation
uh than it would be to a simple equation
原来调香除了技术
还有更像艺术的一面
味道的层次感受
都是调香师谱出来的一曲动听的音乐
Ashley说
调香师之所以比宇航员还少
一个原因呢
是很多人根本不知道有这么个职业
另外一个原因就是要成为调香师
需要花很多年
要坚持不懈
她自己就是个例子
阿什利在15岁的时候
才通过网络
第一次知道有调香师这个职业
下定决心之后
她用了7年的时间拿到化学硕士
又在调香师学校接受了4年训练
才成为一名真正的调香师
有意思的是
虽然调香师的角色很关键
但一款好味道的诞生
更离不开整个团队的合作
每当调香师创作出新的作品之后
大家都会进行
一次盲测品香
来确认能不能产生相似的感受和想象
他们甚至还会专门准备隔离的小房间
避免外界干扰
只为了能更专注的评测气味
我其实有一个问题非常好奇
就是咱们调香师在做香水的时候
是什么来设计这个前中后调的呢
so some of it is evaporation or how long the note lasts on skin
traditionally
we think about it you know if a note you smell
it initially and it evaporates quickly
it's a top note and the notes that stay a bit
longer that you don't smell
till the end are base notes
but like with everything in perfumery
there's always exceptions to the rule for example
patchouli is always classified as a bass note
but in fact a lot of times
you smell patchouli right at the top
so that's why it's so important to really deeply know
learn and memorize your notes
and how they behave
because they all have their own little personality
and even if they're technically a base note
sometimes you really see them on top as well
and this is true for some top notes as well for example
we have a really beautiful quality of bergamot
that's actually upcycled and concentrated
and because of the process that it undergoes
you not only smell it in to you know the top
but also well into the heart
almost to the beginning of the base of a perfume
其实这就跟我们护肤品配方师做
的事特别像每个原料都不是死板的
它们都是活的
是立体的
就像Ashley说的
同一味香料在不同的工艺下
前中后调的表现可能都不一样
护肤原料呢
也是一样
根本不能只用保湿或者用修护几个字
就说清楚一款原料的功能
所以就需要像我们这样的大厨
把它们给搭在一起来
做出真正好用的产品
今天来到这里
最大的收获呢
除了解答了心中的疑惑
把自己也腌入味了
真香舍不得洗衣服
我是配方师星星
如果你喜欢我的溯源系列
如果你愿意随我看遍化妆品行业
欢迎点赞订阅关注我
在调香中心走走看看的时候
我还偶遇了另外一位
非常忙碌的调香师
他的这个桌上全是原料
屋里呢全是他设计的已经上市的作品
包括在中国非常流行的野兽派
他们的家居香薰全都出自他之手